# 大家好 你看這蜂蜜 全部都有好多糖了哦
Hi everyone! Have a look at the honey. They're all very full now.
# 叫兄弟過來 幫忙搞一下
I've asked my buddy to come, and help me deal with it.
# 你看 就這個 全部都站在外面問口啦 不出去採蜜啦
Look! Right this one. They're all standing in front of the door and are not going out for nectar.
# 里面肯定滿了
It must be full inside.
# 因為我們這邊好多野花
Cuz there are a lot of wild flowers here around our site.
# 這秋天 秋天的蜜哦 就叫秋蜜
It's autumn, it's honey in autumn. So it's called autumn honey.
# 你看 這個是蜂王 看到沒有這個
Look! This is the bee queen. See? It's this one.
# 這就是蜂王
This is the bee queen.
# 就這個 就這個蜂王
This one, this is the bee queen.
# 別挖走了 哈哈哈
Don't scoop it away. Hahaha~
# 你看這裡 好多那個蜜蜂崽哦 你看 全部都是
Have a look here. Here are a lot of, of baby bees. Look! They're all here.
# 一卷一卷的 這裡也是哦 (註︰怎樣「一卷一卷」)
They're curling up. Here as well
# 它有封蓋 等下封了蓋之後它就
They're sealing it off. After it's sealed, it's gonna,
# 慢慢地就會把那個蜜蜂會長出來
it's gonna slowly, it's gonna grow into a bee.
# 你看 現在我都不怕蜜蜂啦
Look! Now I am no longer scared of bees.
# 好漂亮哦這個 你看
It's really pretty. Look!
# 這個蜜蜂很漂亮的哦這個 我們家裡的土蜂蜜來的 (註︰他又把蜜蜂說成蜂蜜了)
These bees are really pretty, you know. They're our local honey bees here,
# 不是那種國外的那種大蜂
instead of that kind of big bees from other countries.
# 好多糖哦 你看這是 是不是
A lot of honey. Have a look here. Right?
# 搞一點吃一下看下怎麼樣
Let me have some and see how it is.
# 哎呀 你看
Aya! Look!
# 好甜啊
It's so sweet!
# 今天準備搖點糖出來哦
We're gonna spin out some honey today.
# 好快啊這個 甚麼蜜都可以甩的乾
It's really fast. It can spin out every single drop of honey.
# 叫兄弟過來 過來幫我的忙
I ask my buddy to come, to come and help me out.
# 這個太危險了
It's far too dangerous.
# 不是專業的人不要去搞哦 要不然搞了會
Don't do it unless you're a professional. Otherwise,
# 就把他蟄的鼻青臉腫的
the whole face would get stung and swell like a balloon.
# 現在今年好多糖啊
Now there's a lot of honey this year.
# 哎呀 那麼危險
Eya! It's so dangerous!
# 你看好多糖啊 你看
Look! Here's a lot of honey. Look!
# 這個糖啊
It's honey.
# 我們這裡好多 好多這些 秋天是好多那個野花
There are a lot of, a lot of this kind of, a lot of wild flowers here at our place in autumn.
# 你看 糖就好多 這邊也是 好多哦
Look! Here's plenty of honey. This side too. A lot!
# 搞一塊來
Let me take a piece.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 吃 我吃幾塊來
Let, let me have a few pieces.
# 好啦 直接把它甩 甩出來就好啦
Look! Spin it out, spin it out right away and that's it.
# 甩之前要把這個蓋子 把它
Before spinning, the seal needs to be, it needs to be,
# 割開
cut open.
# 就樣就很多
Then there would be a lot.
# 哇 受不了啦 你看割一塊吃
Wa! I can't resist anymore. I need to cut a piece for myself.
# 歪呦 好啦 拿出來啦
Wayo! Alright! It's out!
# 這個拿去甩 其它的拿去甩 這個就是我來吃
This will be put into the spinner. The rest will be put into the spinner. But this is mine.
# 你看 這個
Look! This,
# 這個蜂蜜
this honey...
# 嗯~
Um~
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 可能現在秋天啦
Perhaps cuz it's autumn now,
# 這個蜂蜜 比那個春蜜更好吃哦
and the honey, tastes even better than spring honey.
# 而且產量很高
And the yield is also very high.
# 整個蜂巢直接咬
Chew the beehive directly.
# 嗯~
Um~
# 好甜
So sweet!
# 你看 這個糖 好多啊
Look! There's, a lot of honey!
# 看見沒有
See?
# 這邊就是那個 蜜蜂崽哦 小崽
One this side are the, the baby bees, the babies.
# 這個我們不要去傷害它 我們只要把那個蜜取掉就好啦
We're not doing harm on them. The honey is all we want. Take the honey, that's it.
# 你看 這邊也是 全是 一片一片的
Look! This side too. All here. They're in clusters.
# 這一邊的就是小蜜蜂 小蜜蜂崽來的
Those on this side are the little bees, the baby bees.
# 所以要 我們不要把它甩出來 就不會破壞到那個小蜂蜜
So we have to, we're not spinning them out. They we won't hurt the little honey bees.
# 好香
Nice!
# 好多花粉在這裡
Here's a lot of pollen.
# 要把這個口要割掉 割掉之後才可以甩哦
This opening needs to be unsealed. We need to unseal it before spinning.
# 要不然蓋子封著甩不出來
We can't get anything when it's covered by the seal.
# 我這有兩 兩餅割開的 直接可以甩掉
These two, two boards here are already unsealed and can be spun right away.
# 誒呦 好快呀
Eyo! It's so fast!
# 甩的差不多了 要換個 換個面
After spinning for a while, it needs to be, needs to be flipped.
# 就那面已經甩完啦 就甩這面
I've already done with that side. So this side now.
# 誒呦
Eyo!
# 還想跑
You wanna run away?
# 就沒有啦
That's all?
# 我以為很多嘞 原來就甩了那麼一丟丟
I thought that it would be a lot. But there's only a tiny little bit.
# 好輕啊 一甩完就沒啦
It's so light now. After spinning, no more honey.
# 這蜜蜂
This bee,
# 想蟄我是不是
does it want to sting me?
# 來呀 讓你蟄 你蟄
C'mon! I let you sting. Sting me!
# 別當真啊
Don't take it seriously.
# 把它倒出來
Let me pour it out.
# 這裡有三四斤啊 這裡
It's almost, two kilograms here.
# 這個就是蜂蜜 你看 就 就那兩三餅 就搖到那麼多出來
This is honey. Look! Such much honey can be spun out from just, just a couple of boards.
# 早上 早上用來裹饅頭 買點饅頭
In the morning, eat it with mantou in the morning. Buy some mantou,
# 放點蜂蜜 就這樣吃
put some honey, and eat right away.
# 這個是沒有過濾哦 這樣看上去就是
This has not been filtered. So it looks a bit...
# 蜂蠟跟那個蜂蜜混在一起 不好看
The beeswax and the honey are mixed together. It doesn't look good.
# 嗯 好香啊
Um! It smells really nice!
# 明天我拿個東西來烤一下
I'm gonna get something to grill tomorrow.
# 刷點蜂蜜
Brush some honey.
# 好啦 我把這個端下下面去
Alright! Let me take it down there,
# 等著先
and keep it there.
# 這裡還有好多
Here's still a lot.
# 來 叫兄弟來甩
Yup! I'll ask my buddy to spin out the honey.
# 我準備去烤東西啦
And I need to prepare for the barbecue.
# 你看 搞了幾隻鴿子回來哦
Look! I got a couple of pigeons back.
# 我們去烤乳鴿
Let's have grilled baby pigeons.
# 這鴿子你看 漂亮吧
Have a look at this pigeon. It's pretty, isn't it?
# 可以喲 哎呀 那麼多肉
Not bad! Aya! It's so meaty.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 屎都嚇出來了
I scared the poo out of it.
# 拿刀來
Let me get my knife.
# 你看 這三隻乳鴿殺好啦 有一個是黑色的
Look! These three baby pigeons are now cleaned and ready. One of them is black.
# 可能就是這樣子的 皮膚比較黑
Perhaps it's just because it has a darker skin.
# 這兩個就比較白 我把內臟取一下 然後就把它架著
These two have whiter skins. I'm gonna remove the guts and then put them onto the frames,
# 把它插上來
pierce them through,
# 就直接烤啦
and then grill them right away.
# 放點鹽
Put some salt.
# 放點油
Put some oil.
# 再削點生薑下去
And then cut some ginger,
# 生薑去腥
to get rid of the bloody smell.
# 加點醬油
Put some soy sauce.
# 加點料酒
Put some cooking wine.
# 給它搓搓背
Give it a back massage.
# 按按腳
and a leg massage.
# 要用力點搓我 這樣味道才能 才能融入它的身體
I need to press it stronger, so that the flavour can be, can be fully integrated with its body.
# 好啦 腌製半個小時
Alright! Marinate it for half an hour.
# 你看 我找了幾根棍子過來哦
Look! I've found a couple of rods.
# 要用棍子給它 綁它一下
I gotta tie them up, with the rods.
# 這樣它就
Then they'll,
# 聽話一點 不會亂跑
they'll behave a bit better, instead of running around.
# 你看 已經綁好啦
Look! They're tied up now.
# 現在它們就聽話啦
They're gonna behave well now.
# 現在就會去烤 三個一起烤 哎呀 美味
I'm gonna grill them, all three together. Aya! Tasty!
# 我到對面那裡去 靠著河邊來
I go to the opposite side over there, by the riverside.
# 到處都長了好多草 看見沒有
The weeds are growing everywhere. See?
# 先這樣烤一下
Grill it for a while here.
# 不然等下不知道烤不烤的熟 它炭太少
Otherwise, I wonder if we can ever make it done. We have too little charcoal.
# 搞點醬料
Get some sauce.
# 從頭刷到尾
Brush from head to tail.
# 它頭上也刷
And on the head too.
# 頭上翅肪上到處 好 轉一圈
One the head, one the wings. Everywhere. Alright! Turn it over.
# 來 給它洗洗澡 這個醬料很香哦 它很喜歡
Yup! Let me give it a bath. This sauce smells really good. It likes the sauce very much.
# 你看這個 去非洲旅行一樣 曬的那麼黑
Look! This one seems to have traveled in Africa. It's so darkly tanned.
# 生出來就是這樣子
It's its inborn colour.
# 剛把它 把它毛褪掉的話一看到這個黑就這個
Once I, once I finished defeathering it, I already saw that it is so black.
# 所以不是我們搞(烤)的 本來就是那麼黑
So it's not because of us. It's not burnt. It has always been black.
# 哎呀 這裡有個小龍蝦哦 那麼大的小龍蝦
Aya! Here's a crayfish. It's such a big crayfish.
# 哇你看 這裡有隻那麼大的小龍蝦
Wa! Look! Here's such a big crayfish.
# 來 給它烤烤火 它可能冷了
C'mon! We've set a fire for it. Perhaps it feels very cold now.
# 要划一下 不划一下烤下熟
I need to slice it. Otherwise it would take forever.
# 嗯 差不多熟了
Um! It's almost done now.
# 搞點調料
Put some seasoning.
# 這昨天割出來的蜂蜜哦 很新鮮的哦
This is the honey harvested yesterday. It's really fresh, you know.
# 開始刷蜂蜜啦
Let's put on the honey.
# 現在蜂蜜多的很
Honey is now plentiful.
# 但是不能浪費哦
But wasting is never an option.
# 下面
Underneath,
# 下面接著
catch it underneath.
# 哇
Wa!
# 全身都裹著蜂蜜
The whole body is coated with honey.
# 這樣 這樣才好吃
That, that makes it a delicacy.
# 從頭上淋一兩下
Pour some above its head.
# 翅肪上也淋一下
And also on the wings
# 烤個兩分鐘就可以直接吃哦
Two more minutes. And then we can start eating right away.
# 好啦 準備開吃開吃
Alright! Ready, ready!
# 放這裡來
Put it here.
# 放在這裡就行啦
Just put it here. It's fine.
# 嘗一下 嘗一下味道怎麼樣
Let me have a try, have a try and see how it tastes.
# 我吃一個啊
I'll have one.
# 好香啊 吃這一個
It smells good! I'll have this one.
# 嗯~
Um~
# 好香啊
It smells really nice!
# 真的好好吃啊 不騙你們的
It tastes really good! No kidding!
# 你看 漂亮吧
Look! Isn't it pretty?
# 烤的酥酥的
It's crispy.
# 太好吃了
It's really fantastic!
# 來 哈吧 小哈吧 哈吧狗
Hey! Pug, puggy, pug!
# 來 吃骨頭
C'mon! The bone is yours.
# 這個烤鴿子好吃 這個烤鴿子
The grilled pigeon tastes really good, this grilled pigeon.
# 好久都沒吃過這麼好吃的東西了 (註︰好像很難照意思去完全翻譯而又不顯得突兀)
I haven't had anything so tasty for quite a long time.
# 嗯 大胖狗
Um! Big Chubby!
# 嘿 別掉了哦
Hey! Don't drop it!
# 不能浪費食物
Never waste food!
# (娃哈哈) 我要搞個頭給它吃 (註︰字幕沒有寫，那黑白狗叫娃哈哈)
Wahaha, let me give him the head.
# 頭哦 包含好多營養的哦 (註︰其實我聽到︰「娃哈哈 好多營養的哦」)
It's head. It's very nutritious.
# 它搶不到
He lost to Big Cubby!
# 你看 這個鴿子加了蜂蜜 好好吃啊
Look! This pigehon, with honey, tastes really good.
# 甜甜的
It's kind of sweet.
# 蜜汁乳鴿哦 這樣搞
Honey grilled pigeon, so it's called.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 吃多兩口
I have a few more bites.
# 把那個火滅一下 回去啦
Let's put out the fire, and go back now.